Hao Jiang, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Fellow Harvard John A. Paulson School Of Engineering And Applied Sciences 150 Western Ave, Boston, MA 02134 (315)267-6271 hajiang@seas.harvard.edu https://harperjiang.github.io

I am an accomplished Postdoctoral Researcher at Harvard University. My research involves self-designing blockchain and large language models. They have many potential applications in a variety of industries. Previously, I earned my Ph.D. in Computer Science from the University of Chicago, where I specialized in Databases, Distributed Systems, and Machine Learning. I have authored several publications in leading academic conferences. With six years of experience as a Software Engineer, I am well-versed in Java, C++, and Python. I also have experience leading small teams.

Education

The University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

Ph.D. Computer Science

2015 - 2021

- Advisor: Aaron J. Elmore

D / 1 NX

Clarkson University

Potsdam, NY

M.Sc. Computer Science

2012 - 2015

- Advisors: Jeanna N. Matthews

Fudan University

Shanghai, China

B.Sc. Computer Science

2001 - 2005

- Advisor: Liang Zhang

Publications

- 1. Chunwei Liu, **Hao Jiang**, John Paparrizos, Aaron J. Elmore Decomposed Bounded Floats for Fast Compression and Queries VLDB 2021
- 2. **Hao Jiang**, Chunwei Liu, John Paparrizos, Aaron J. Elmore *Good to the last bit: Data-Driven Encoding with CodecDB SIGMOD 2021*
- 3. **Hao Jiang**, Chunwei Liu, Qi Jin, John Paparrizos, Aaron J. Elmore, *PIDS: Attribute Decomposition for Improved Compression and Query Performance in Columnar Storage*, VLDB 2020
- 4. Chunwei Liu, McKade Umbenhower, **Hao Jiang**, Aaron J. Elmore, *Mostly Order Preserving Dictionaries*, *ICDE 2019*
- 5. **Hao Jiang**, Aaron J. Elmore, Boosting Data Filtering on Columnar Encoding with SIMD, DaMon 2018
- 6. Dixin Tang, **Hao Jiang**, Aaron J. Elmore, Adaptive Concurrency Control: Despite the Looking Glass, One Concurrency Control Does Not Fit All, CIDR 2017
- 7. **Hao Jiang**, Yaoqing Liu, Jeanna N. Matthews, *IP Geolocation Estimation using Neural Networks with Stable Landmarks*, *IEEE INFOCOM Workshop GI 2016*

8. Wenjin Hu, Long Zhang, **Hao Jiang**, Jeanna N. Matthews, A Quantitative Study of Virtual Machine Live Migration, CAC 2013

Research Experience

Harvard University

Boston, MA

Postdoctoral Researcher with Prof. Stratos Idreos

Oct 2021 - Now

- Blockchain Calculator: Build a self-designing blockchain system that adapts to workloads to provide high-throughput and low-latency
- Detachable Memory in Large Language Models: Develop a small and detachable memory component for large language models. These components maintain domain knowledge and long-term memory and can be trained independently from the main LLM. They grant the LLM different abilities.

The University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

Research Assistant under Prof. Aaron J. Elmore

Sept. 2015 - Aug. 2021

- CoLSM: Lightweight Encoding in LSM-trees Explore using lightweight encodings to LSM-trees to improve lookup efficiency. Design a LSM-tree that supports using different data structure at each level to improve merge performance.
- PIDS: Exploring Unsupervised Pattern Inference in String Attributes Design a new compression algorithm that discover patterns in string attributes, and uses the pattern to extract and compress sub-attributes independently. This result is published on VLDB.
- Encoding-Aware Columnar Database Design and build a columnar database query engine that uses encoding knowledge to speed up database queries. Our query engine executes queries 5-30x faster than the state-of-the-art. This result is published on SIGMOD.
- Data-Driven Database Encoding Selection. Using Machine Learning Techniques to select the most efficient data encoding schema for a given columnar database.
- SBoost: Using SIMD Instruction to speed up Database Operator. Design an innovative algorithm for querying compressed data without decompression using SIMD Instructions.
- Auto-Encoder in Data Compression. Design an auto-encoder network to compress data for approximation queries.
- Pattern as a Foreign Language. Using Recurrent Neural Network to discover and extract hidden pattern from database columns.
- Distributed Storage on ZCCloud. Design and implement a simulator that study the system availability and performance of Cassandra distributed key-value store running on Zero-Cabon Cloud Datacenter platforma using stranded power.

Clarkson University

Potsdam, NY

Research Assistant under Prof. Jeanna N. Matthews

Sept. 2012 - Jul. 2015

- Internet Toplogy Platform. Design, implement and experiment several heuristic based partitioning methods on Internet Topology. Experiment on building a Internet Topology Platform support thirdparty data analysis programs to access Internet structure with ease.
- GreenDataCenter Project. Participate in GreenDataCenter (GDC) Project. Design and
 implement a simulation environment to study the feasibility of using pure green energy, such
 as solar and wind to power distribute data center and provide service with high availability.
- IP Geolocation. Proposed an innovative method of locating the physical location of arbitrary IP address with a two-tier neural network. Independently designed and implemented the system.

Phishing website detection with logo recognition. Used SVM to extract the embedded logos of known websites from a large image to identify phishing websites based on these logos. Independently designed and implemented the system.

Fudan University

Shanghai, China

Research Assistant under Prof. Liang Zhang

Sept. 2003 - Jul. 2005

 Grid Computing. Study the feasibility of using IBM Globus Platform to build a grid-computing system for bio-informatic computation and database service.

Work Experience

Harvard University

Cambridge, MA

Postdoctoral Fellow

Oct. 2021 - Present

- Research on Blockchain and Large Language Models

Facebook Inc.

Menlo Park, CA

Software Engineer Intern

July. 2018 - Sept. 2018

- Design, implement and evaluate a load balance algorithm for PHP requests

Baidu Inc.

Shanghai, China

System Architect

Sept. 2011 - Aug. 2012

- Design and implement a customizable MySQL replication framework. This framework intercepts message sent by a master database during MySQL master-slave replication, rewrite it with user provided function and send it to slave database. This framework allows an easy customization of replication behaviors.
- BigData Analysis System using Hadoop. Lead a 4-developer team to design and develop a
 Hadoop-based BigData analysis system. The system processes a daily data volume of over 10
 terabytes.

OOCL Co. Ltd.

Shanghai, China

Senior Software Engineer

Sept. 2005 - Sept. 2011

- Production Server JVM Performance Tuning. Design and implement a log analysis system for production environment JVM resource leak and memory leak tracing and tuning.
- Design and optimization of an accounting system containing billions of rows and processing millions of queries hourly based on Oracle DBMS.

Teaching Experience

Introduction to Database

The University of Chicago

Teaching Assistant

Spring 2018

- Holding office hours and answer student questions

Computer Security

The University of Chicago Autumn 2015. Spring 2016

Teaching Assistant

Holding office hours and answer student questions

Introduction to Computer Science

Clarkson University

Teaching Assistant

Fall, 2014

Holding Labs, lecutures and recitation classes

Calculus I Clarkson University
Teaching Assistant Fall 2013

- Led recitation classes guiding students through difficult problems and reviewing course

Linear Algebra and Differential Equations

Clarkson University

Fall 2012

Teaching Assistant

material.

- Proctoring exams and grading

Presentations

- CodecDB: A Compression Aware Columnar Database
 - SIGMOD 2021, Online, June 2021.
- Attribute Decomposition for String Compression
 - VLDB 2020, Online, June 2020.
- Efficient Query on Compressed Data with SIMD
 - DaMoN 2018, Austin, TX. June 2018.
- Data-Driven Lightweight Encoding Selection
 - CERES Research Summit The University of Chicago, Chicago, IL. March 2017.
- An Log-based Dynamic Partitioning Method
 - System Seminar The University of Chicago CS System Group, Chicago, IL. Oct 2016.
- IP Geolocation using Two-tier Neural Network
 - 6th Global Internet Symposium, San Francisco, CA. Apr 2016.

Participation in Workshops and Conferences

ACM SIGMOD Online

SIGMOD 2021 June 2021

Very Large Database Online

VLDB 2020 June 2020

Very Large Database Los Angeles, CA

VLDB 2019 May 2019

ACM SIGMOD
SIGMOD/PODS 2018
Houston, TX
May 2018

ACM SIGMOD/PODS Chicago, IL SIGMOD/PODS 2017 May 2017

1st Workshop on Data Management and End-to-End Machine Learning Chicago, IL DEEM 2017 May 2017 Center for Unstoppable Computing Research Summit Chicago, IL The University of Chicago March 2017 Quantum Computing Symposium Argonne, IL Argonne National Lab May 2016 6th Global Internet Symposium San Francisco, CA IEEE INFOCOM 2016 April 2016

Technical Skills

- Computer Science
 - Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Optimization, Parallel Programming, Database,
 Distributed Systems, Data Structure
- Programming Languages
 - Java, Scala, C/C++, Python, Go, Matlab, Javascript, HTML/CSS